[music]
The press that's enshrined in our
constitution, our first amendment, the
free press, was often a scurless press.
We're supposed to trouble the
government. We're supposed to challenge
the government.
>> The US drops thousands of tons of bombs
on the Vietnamese people every day. How
can Nixon claim to be upset about a few
eggs thrown at him? We were trying to
exercise every tactical strategy we
could [music] to stop the war in
Vietnam.
>> Where Ramparts really gets liftoff is
when Warren recruits Bob Shear.
>> Bob does the interview with Jimmy Carter
where Jimmy Carter says he has lust in
his heart.
>> If you think crimes have been conducted
in your name by your government, then
you have an obligation to become a
whistleblower. We are not the
indispensable agents of history. When we
come to believe we are, we do much more
damage than we do good.
He's of the same line as Walter Litman
and Murray Kempton
and Izzy Stone.
These are journalists who are
essentially historians,
but they're historians dealing with
living history. They don't have to go
back to the [music] to the books to what
other people have written. Maybe because
I grew up among immigrants, you know,
where I grew up in the Bronx. I mean,
foreign languages were everywhere and
everybody was coming from some other
place and had some story and and I grew
up loathing loathing an Americaentric
view of the world. I always had the idea
that everybody matters. My parents were
garment workers and I knew they
mattered. I knew their friends mattered.
I knew the people in my neighborhood
mattered. Some fell off. my father to
take me down at the Bowery, show me
people who were lined up to get food. No
one ever gave me a reason to think that
these people were not equal to me and to
anyone else. I was always raised with
the idea there was an inherent value to
human life.
What
I don't feel I know is what makes you
tick. What happened to you at 11 or 12
or 14 or earlier
that turned you on to the kind of
citizen you are?
>> Oh, it was just in the air. I was born
in 36.
My father and mother, my mother was the
other woman. Uh, my
>> What do you mean the other woman?
>> My father was married, had couple of
children. They met on a picket line.
They were both garment workers. My
father was a German Protestant. My
mother was a Russian Jew. They happened
to fall in love. I [snorts] got my
father's name. I knew I was a good
street hustler. I was working when I was
12 and a half. I could make deals. I
could run orders. I could
>> What kind of deals?
>> You know, anything anybody wanted. I
could sell sodas at the Guardian. I
could do garden. I could do it at Lewis
Stadium. I was a good hustler. And
>> what's the cleverest thing you ever
hustled as a kid?
>> What was your cleverest hustle? Oh, my
cleverest thing was standing in front of
the garden and looking for lawn like a
street urchin. Hey, you missed it. You
got an extra ticket, guys. I don't know.
Well, let me see if she shows up. The
girlfriend didn't show up. He'd give me
the tickets, maybe give me both. I run
around to the other side of the garden
and sell them.
>> That's my I was doing that three, four
nights a week. Yeah, I was it was called
mooching,
>> you know. But let me ask you because you
know I have to say something for but
you've been my role model. Okay. I don't
want to embarrass you and I don't not
giving you making you responsible.
>> But you know, I feel the same way about
you. All you've got on me is youth
>> and smarts. No. [laughter]
And a lot of smarts when I first
>> Wait a minute. This is my interview of
you.
>> I was sort of born into a environment in
which you could not avoid politics
for all sorts of reasons. I was born in
1936 in Bronx Hospital, April 4th, 1936.
And my father lost his job that day.
Uh, and this was for him the beginning
of the depression. He didn't get it back
until the [music] war came along. My
father's family were German. My mother's
uh Jewish. My father's family in Germany
was killing my mother's family in
Lithuania. [music]
Those were all live issues. relatives
would arrive from the respective old
countries. So half my relatives in New
York were German Protestants, half were
Russian Jews. I went from one to the
other. And what united them was
politics. They all were on the [music]
progressive side of things. My father
had been a wobbly and uh socialist and
very briefly even a communist was thrown
out at a party [music] for leading a
wildcat strike at the New York Nitty
Mills. My childhood [music] game was
killing Kraut except my father was
clearly a kraut. Had a strong German
accent and all my German relatives on
the other hand they were very [music]
strong anti-fascist. They were more
strong anti-fascist than anyone else I
knew because and they were particularly
have been involved with Spain and you
know supporting the struggle against
fascism in Spain.
My mother came over from Lithuania when
she [music] was 21. My mother uh in
Lithuania had been involved with this
group, the Jewish Socialist Bund. And
>> [music]
>> uh two of her sisters were killed by the
Zars police uh organizing. So this
group, the Jewish Socialist Bund, uh
used my mother to carry messages in her
hair. And one terrifying scene, she
[music] went to a town to deliver this
message to someone who had already been
arrested. And she was put up near the
prison [music] by some sympathizers. and
she could hear the fellow being tortured
all night. That's it. It was an
important family story. Her group had
been for a short time allied with the
Bolsheviks and then Lenin denounced
their group and suddenly they were
hunted people. This revolution that they
had fought for was now gone south for
them.
My mother knew
negative things about the Soviet Union
quite early that [music] that she was a
sympathizer in that she still felt the
revolution was a progressive agency up
to a point. You got to remember New York
City Council when I was growing up had
three communists on the city council.
[music] Everybody forgets about the
history of the communists in in the
United States. They were very involved
and maybe at the center of the whole
civil rights movement [music] as they
had been very important to the labor
movement.
>> It was a question of survival for you.
>> Yeah. Well, when I read Margaret Sanger
in the early birth control movement, I'm
the person they didn't think had to be
born, right?
>> Parents didn't have good jobs and, you
know, and so forth. Uh, how do you take
care of a little kid? My mother's a
garment worker. I'm parked in a carriage
by my uncle Leon's fruit stand and uh
you know I can to this day here four
water for frock water from Florida.
Florida. Look, I was raised by the women
in my neighborhood cuz my mother was
working. So the women who stayed home,
they'd made sure I Hey, Bobby, you got
to have some milk, you know, or did you
get some lunch? You know, and uh you
know, Miss Nusbomb down on the third
floor, you know, I had to check in with
her when I came in, you know, as a third
grader. And I would say among my circle
of friends these days, I'm the only one
that's actually been food deprived. You
know, we we food was an issue. Okay. So
when I was 12 and a half,
uh there was a Myerovich's grocery store
right on the corner of the of this
project at Coups and uh I was already
starting to deliver orders for my so my
got this idea. He had a big station
wagon that he would get the build
Milwick delivery to his store and then
he put it on the corners around this
project which was like basically three
blocks going that way and then he would
have kids deliver the milk at 4:00 or 5
in the morning only. No one other
parents would let their kids do it. So I
was the only one
and my father thought that yes you have
a job you know that's good you know and
when I was doing my milk deliveries
but let's see this is about 48 1948 49
I would made this discovery that cuz I'm
the only one out there [music] and I'm
seeing all these books by the garbage
cans and I remember two in particular
that I dragged home. Uh, one was the
collected works of Stalin.
I think it was 12 or 13 volumes. It was
kind of red covers and one was the
collected works of, amazingly enough,
Thomas Jefferson. They were big green
volumes and the collected letters and
works of Thomas Jefferson. I think there
were like 20 of them or some 25 of them.
And I brought them to this tiny little
apartment we had. I had them like under
my bed.
That showed you the temper of the time.
People were afraid. The FBI was all over
this neighborhood. We call them the
Phoebe. And you could tell them by their
antennas, unmarked cars.
And people were arrested.
And I brought the Jefferson with me to
graduate school in Berkeley. So I had
them with me up till then.
Look, it was an atmosphere that could
have soured me
and I could have become uh very out for
myself,
you know. I could have I want to feather
my nest.
>> What's the strongest reason why you
didn't?
>> Cuz I enjoyed people. I really did. I I
found my salvation in on the street
corner in the candy store and neighbors
uh playing ball. Uh I I just liked it. I
liked the people there. Was there
anything in all of the the experience
you just described that suggests
journalism would follow?
>> I liked everybody's story. Everybody had
a story and I had no hierarchy of who's
in story is important. But somebody once
said about journalism, in any story I
want to know who's getting screwed and
who's doing the screwing. And that has
been the the motto of my whole life.
Okay? I don't like people getting
screwed over. I want to know who's
screwing them over.
I arrived in Berkeley and what was
really exciting was not Berkeley. What
was exciting was North Beach and that
was the Beats. Beats and jazz.
Tremendous jazz in San Francisco as good
as there was anywhere in the world. And
you had the Beatix and the Beatnicks
were reading poems to jazz and the
marriage of poetry [music] and jazz.
So I wrote a piece about Allan Ginsburg
which was an attack on the traditional
left and it was called poet is priest in
root and branch kind of a student lefty
magazine saying listen the old left was
all wrong and Ginsburg is right.
>> Bob and I had hadn't gotten together
yet. So I think he showed up in in my
life anyway [music] in 1958
and he was what he proudly announced to
me a term I had never heard a red diaper
baby and there were almost all red
diaper babies David Horowitz among them
probably the most left-wing of the whole
group
>> it was an incredible group and we put
out this publication root and branch and
so Harowitz who then soon after wrote a
book called student celebrates quotes
[snorts]
something I wrote and student showing
the free spirit of the new left and how
we were not at all inclined to be
communists or suppress free speech but
quite the opposite and I was held up as
the poster child
all of us rejected uh these communist
countries we all knew they were
totalitarian that was not an issue now
Harowitz however rejected it from
atroskious position they should have
permanent revolution. Others, I think
Maurice would be one who rejected it
more from a social democratic position
and democracy, workers control. And the
negative on Berkeley was that it was now
a conservative suppressed campus because
California public education, higher
education had come under a late variant
of of McCarthyism. And we had the big
loyalty oath battle or they had had the
big loyalty oath battle and the federal
unamerican activities committee which
was uh you know blacklisting people
which was getting people fired and
imprisoning them.
That became actually one of the first
big demonstrations in the Bay Area was
against UAE a very important partition
which I participated in that first year
that I went out there. And so we planned
to have a demonstration, a peaceful
demonstration picketing against the
House on American Activities Committee.
>> We met with a few other graduate
students at Berkeley. We said, "Hey,
they're coming here. Uh, we should do
this." We put out the word and so forth.
>> So, we organized, we made signs, we
organized the picket, went and uh
picketed.
And our great concern actually was that
it not get disruptive. This was, you
know, early on. You know, this was
before the 60s, just 1960, and there
hadn't been much of this.
>> But what was great was somehow or other
we got to talk to to Harry Bridges
before that.
>> Harry Bridges was himself a target of
VUAC. So you had your warehouseman
workers, your longshore and in those
days longshore was still a big activity
unloading uh boats by you know hand and
track and uh so you had a strong labor
movement that was didn't want you coming
there and harassing people.
So that day of infamy there were over I
mean I hope I'm not exaggerating there
were several thousand doc workers who
showed up. Okay. So, that really was a
danger that you have ordinary workers
from a left union that are now marching
there.
>> And so, we thought there'd be agent
provocators and so forth who would come
and become more disruptive and we were
there to hand out our leaflets and give
our message of what was wrong with you.
>> But there were these kids from Stanford
University who went into the building
and banged on the doors down with the
committee. down with the committee.
Abolish Uack, right?
>> And the next thing you knew, our whole
crowd out there on the [snorts] street
rushed into into the building.
>> Sure enough, of course, all of a sudden,
the cops come
racing out.
>> They brought out these hoses and
flooding down the steps. The steps were
quite uh steep and slippery and we, you
know, swept down the hosed us down the
stairs and people were arrested. The
cops come beating people with their
clubs on the head. One of the kids, I
still remember her, Mary Macintosh. He
was bleeding like this. And this is not
a joke. They come in and they're going
to swing it. Bobby says, "Wait a minute.
I'm anti-communist."
Guy says, "I don't care what kind of
communist [laughter] you are.
And there's this flood of water coming
down the steps and people are slipping
and sliding and hurting themselves aside
from the police brutality. And there's
absolute mayhem.
So then my memory is we kind of went
into triage there trying to get help to
people who were bleeding and you know
hurting in different ways and that
became the news story. And what I can
tell you categorically is we did not
create it.
It was a disaster for the students. But
symbolically it became a rallying point
because students would show up at other
uh demonstrations or rallies that we
were organizing who didn't know a damn
thing about UAC but now identified with
fellow students because they couldn't
believe this is America and students are
getting beat up over the head by
policemen. The UAC demonstration was a
very big part of the development of the
Bay Area. The connection of all these
movements, the peace movement, the civil
rights movement. It was also UAC's
moment was over.
He took off for Cuba almost immediately
after the revolutionaries came to power
sometime in 1960. you know, when it was
still easy to go there.
>> Cuba in the first couple years of the
Cuban revolution, the Beats, believe it
or not, were playing a role. That's why
Lawrence Furling Getty wrote his
thousand fearful words for Fidel
and they had a publication called Lunis
in the official Communist Party
Revolution newspaper. The people running
that Monday edition, they all thought
the Beats were kind of their role model,
not Karl [music] Marx. and they printed
Ginsburg and Ferlling Getty and all
these people and he came back he said
Zyllet it's amazing what's going on down
there this is a genuine revolution we
got to write about it
at the time we were making speeches and
this is no exaggeration okay I would
speak not as long as Fidel but sometimes
three or four hours okay and as the
classes would change so each at each
each hour there was a new [laughter]
new masses uh to agitate and eventually
there were really thousands of I kid you
not there were thousands of students at
uh Bunell Plaza then Bob would take
over.
So we were like the Bobsy twins. I mean
we were agitators
and um
pamphleteers
and speech makers and felling came up
after one of our speeches and he said
I'd like you guys to write a book for
me. Okay, I really like the way you guys
talk and I would like you to write a
book for me for you know City Lights
Books. I'll be glad to publish it but
you got to get it to me while everything
is still you know in the air. So we
wrote this book and handed him the
manuscript [laughter] and he he had this
look on his face as how is he going to
tell these guys. This is not the book I
expected you to write. It has footnotes
and it has an appendix with tables. What
were you thinking? I wanted a broadside
like you guys talk. So we were, you
know,
so upset and I don't know how we got in
touch with Barney Rosset at Grove Books
who at the time was publishing the kinds
of books that were banned
and he published a book.
>> Cuban tragedy in our hemisphere was the
Grove Press version. And so at the end
of this whole thing and here I had a
book and I was very proud of it. It was
a big deal. We were both graduate
students and I just want Maurice to get
a lot of credit for it because I learned
a lot from him. In my case, I perished
publishing because I had a fellowship at
the Center for Chinese Studies and we
had some real harsh Cold War hawks who
were on the board of the Center for
Chinese Studies which was basically a
part of a CIA front and they engineered
the yanking of my money that I would not
be a fellow.
Even then it was clear that Bob had a
reporter's flare that he was a
journalist.
>> I think the thesis of our book was
correct that this that that and I think
it's the connection with the Vietnam
project which came from me right after
which is whatever you think of these
communist governments around the world.
They were not mere extensions of the
Soviet Union.
What made you what? How did you happen
to come down on the side of the Bill of
Rights, the Declaration of Independence?
>> It was a very simple choice. At City
College, I was studying engineering
and because that was what I was good at
and I could make a living and I went
down to sit in a class and I ended up
taking called Basic Issues of American
Democracy.
Everything was an issue. Everything.
what does free speech mean? What is the
fourth amend what is what does any mean?
What are the values on both sides? And
it was basically a debate,
>> you know, what what is this constitution
all about? Basic issues of American
democracy. We talked about segregation.
We talked about war and peace. Talk
about everything. And I thought, wow.
>> And you knew what side you were on going
in. No, I like No, I like the fact that
there were issues whether it was about
McCarthyism, whether it was about the
Korean War, it was all up for grabs and
you could get a different piece of it.
And then I discovered the 42nd Street
Library and the City College Library and
and I could go down there and I could
come back a few days later and know more
than my professor did about it, you
know, and try to persuade him. And I
would say that learning as as an
activity, as a a sport, as a source of
joy, uh became the main thing going.
>> He was a graduate student in Berkeley. I
told Bob, "Leave Berkeley and come to
the reality of North Beach." He worked
at the store about 3, four years, I
think,
>> at City Lights. You know, it was a great
bookstore. People have never seen City
Lights. It's still there.
My job was to open the store at 10:00.
I'd open up all the new magazines coming
in. I'd open up the books that came in
and, you know, they'd be all around me
on the counter. I could be there, like I
say, two hours early. I had to sweep the
place from the night before and clean it
up. And then very often I close the
place and I got a hell of an education
there. And that's how I got interested
in Vietnam. I open up a magazine, China
Quarterly, and I open up a French
publication, Newville Observator.
These people were writing about the
stupidity that the Americans were
following in Vietnam and not learning
the lessons from the French.
Then I went over to Berkeley to check on
Vietnam. And what happened was I found
one day a packet of papers and there was
nobody had opened this up. There was
some dust on it and a ribbon around it.
So I blew off the dust and opened this
up. This was all about how Michigan
State Police Project had trained the
police in in Vietnam and Saigon and
Stanley Shinbam who had been the
co-director of the Michigan State
Project. By that time he was a source of
mine in doing this research. He had been
used to be cover for the CIA project and
it had to do with torture, had to do
with the Seawward police, had to do with
all of this. All by way of shoring up no
deny, the guy that the US had been
picked to be the George Washington of
South Vietnam when it decided it was
going to not honor the Geneva Accords
and not have elections and that Ho Chi
Min would have won those elections. Paul
Kraner who was editing a magazine called
the Realist magazine. I said I could
write something about this and he said
that's good. And I said but I should go
to Vietnam. He said where's that or
something? He didn't know. It was pretty
early on. I said, "Well, like for
$1,467.36,
I can get this ticket right now this
afternoon, roundtrip ticket, and I can
go and pursue these stories that I'm
interested in." And bless him, he uh he
had just made a bunch of money off his
[__] communism posters.
He wrote a check out and I got and got
the ticket I think that afternoon
and I went to Vietnam.
What happened was I wrote this pamphlet
and the pamphlet took off.
>> One of the first things Bob ever wrote
was a pamphlet [music]
called How the US Got Involved in
Vietnam
and it sold over a million copies
[music] and it was hugely influential
and people uh still come up to us and
say, [music]
you know, you got me to change my
opinion of the Vietnam War. You got me
to come out against the Vietnam War. I
read that and felt if id read this in '
64 or 65 I would never have gone to
Vietnam. It wasn't just that I thought
it was a loser. I would no longer have
seen it as a legitimate struggle for us
to be in. It was clear from the real
history of Vietnam and and Bob was
better at that. He his account was
better as an account that was available
from almost anyone else at that point of
the American involvement. Um uh it was
clear that what we had here was a neoc
colonial an imperial involvement where
we were um in we were governing the
place through our proxies basically
which meant that it had no legitimacy
from an American point of view as I saw
it.
>> Thousands of young men in this district
are being asked to kill in Vietnam and
possibly be killed. They know next to
nothing about the history or culture of
Vietnam. They have been continuously
lied to by their administration. The
news about Vietnam has been continuously
manipulated. The American position in
Vietnam has been continuously distorted
by the administration.
This campaign is aimed at opposing the
war. It is my position that the United
States should never have become involved
in Vietnam, should never have stayed in
Vietnam, and should now get out. I ran
for Congress against a Democratic
candidate, Jeffrey Coalen, who was
supposed to be a liberal guy, but he was
supporting Johnson and War, and that was
his whole defense. She sure doesn't know
what he's talking about. I've been at
these briefings. I know what the
communists are up to. I know what's
going on in Vietnam, you know, and it
was a big lie because it was all based
on the idea of a monolithic communist
movement and the Vietnamese were just
part of an international communist
conspiracy. And that was garbage and the
government knew it was garbage. And
there was a group of of radical or
liberal professors at Berkeley called
the faculty peace committee. So they met
with Bobby and I and they asked him if
he would consider running for Congress
because Bobby was such a good speaker
and was so deeply, you know, um [snorts]
involved in the history of Vietnam, the
knowledge that he had. But when he ran
for Congress, we were trying to exercise
every tactical strategy we could to stop
the war in Vietnam. We could be stopping
troop trains.
[cheering]
>> We could be getting arrested in some
demonstration.
>> And we could be doing all of the above
at the same time.
>> I think we're making this demonstration
today because we want to confront the
citizens of this community with the
enormity of this crime to bring the
reality of that war home to them. And
this is in fact our war. all of our
wars, whether we are against it, whether
we parade against it, or we are for it,
is a war wage in our name. And as one
who has had to travel through villages
and both, South Vietnam and in Cambodia,
which were bombed out by American bombs
and confront the people in those
villages whose parents, whose sons,
whose sisters died as a result of that
bombing, I can tell you they held me
accountable as much as they would hold
someone who supports the war accountable
because I was an American. I look like
an American. It was my government.
There were some friendships that broke
up over Bobby running for Congress. So,
he did get kind of the ultralleft. I
won't even call it that, but there was a
part of the left that was harshly
critical because he was in that arena
running for Congress, but I don't think
he and I felt I mean, we've always felt
like this is just another tactic to try
and stop the war. I knew something then
that I learned painfully while I ran for
office. That whatever your intentions,
you're going to give the same speech
seven times a day. You're going to look
for the applause lines. You're going to
simplify it a bit. And I started to not
like myself
very much doing that.
>> It's interesting. Bobby is probably one
of the best speakers in my whole life. I
mean to this date, but in my whole life
with him, he would worry worry every
speech. Like he'd sit in the bathtub for
hours, you know, trying to
just to to I guess get himself ready,
but he he was never comfortable like
glib.
>> In 1966, I vividly remember when Sheer
ran for Congress on a two-prong platform
to end poverty in Oakland and end the
war in Vietnam. and I was a 14-year-old
uh nervous Nelly for sheer as the uh
slogan had it. That was the phrase that
uh was used by the Johnson
administration and I think Johnson
himself or at least his speech writers
to caricature and castigate those who
questioned uh the efficacy and
legitimacy of American intervention in
Vietnam. Then I still have campaign
buttons.
It was then that I met in passing his
24year-old campaign manager uh the uh
ineitable Alice Waters.
>> I ended up uh driving him to some of the
engagements that he had uh around
Berkeley and other places and I would
sit in the audience if you will and I
could have heard it over and over again.
I did hear it over and over again, but
it it just became
sort of my thinking about the war. And
when he lost, I didn't want to have
anything to do with politics again. I
always tell him the story that then when
he lost, I opened shape.
>> We stepped on a lot of toes in this area
in the last five months. I don't sound
like the ordinary candidate. I don't
look like the ordinary candidate. And
the fact that 29,000 people were willing
to vote for me, made that commitment
indicates a very serious commitment to a
new style of politics.
>> I came what I say is dangerously close
to winning.
>> Sheer Darily lost the election,
garnering something on the order of 45%
of the vote, but it was, as you know,
regarded as a bellweather election, and
it paved the way for Ronald Delum's
victory two years later. So one night I
hear this candidate running for
Congress, [clears throat]
Bob Sheer, this incredibly articulate
guy [clears throat]
who was speaking with such clarity
and such integrity. I came back to my
guys and I said, "Man, I just met a bad
white dude."
[laughter] And they said, "Really?" I
said, "Yeah, you got to hear this guy.
Mind you, I'm still running a magazine.
Basically running it because I'm the
managing editor by that point. And there
were people pissed off at the magazine.
What the [__] you running for Congress
for? You're supposed to be running a
magazine. We're an international
magazine. You know, people reading us
all over the world and you're putting
around in Oakland. I do think Ramparts
was gang busters. It was [__] gang
busters. and and the whole thing was the
people we were taking on.
We were the that breath of fresh air. We
were the it's what the the Berkeley was.
It was what this free speech movement
was. Well, Ramparts, you know, it was
another manifestation. But in the world
of journalism, in world of journalism,
for that I have to really give Hinkle a
lot of credit. We were always
journalists and he was going to
transform journalism.
>> Where Ramparts really gets liftoff is
when Warren recruits Bob Shear. So Bob
Shear brings that kind of political
analysis.
>> Warren is really smart too and he was
not politically radical or ideologically
radical but he was a troublemaker, a
muckreaker [music]
and that's the part that he really
loved. And that's why we ended up at the
magazine ended up doing, you know,
exposing the CIA because he was a
risktaker. And so here we have Bob who's
more the intellectual leftist, you know,
more has more of the sort of
philosophical political history of the
left, [music] socialism, communism, and
here's Warren who's like, "Yeah, let's
go, you know, blow it up, you [laughter]
know, let's let's, you know, uh, take
them on fearless." So that's one thing I
loved about Warren. The two of them
together were really a dynamic duo.
>> I go to work in Ramparts and start 6364.
But one thing I do is uh put the
magazine squarely on the side of raising
questions about this Vietnam war thing.
But you know the women were we were in
these lowly jobs which had lower pay and
uh we were expected to work all night to
to put the the magazine to bed. We that
was you know that's what you do in
journalism and so we did that but the
guys would go out to Vaness and put it
on the credit card for the magazine and
we had to pay for our own. So, I
organized I organized the women and and
we we protested and we we got our meals
paid for, too.
I mean, we all loved being there. I
learned a tremendous amount and it was
very exciting because we were the only
publication basically in the United
States challenging the Vietnam War in
the beginning, challenging all kinds of
things. It was amazing work going on.
Gene Marine and David Welch and Saul
Stern. They were they would and and of
course Bob.
>> You had the traditional liberal
magazines like The Nation and the New
Republic, but they didn't have anywhere
near the impact that Ramparts did.
>> So what Rampart did was they said,
"Let's let's put some resources into
this. Let's make it look like Time
magazine
and let's go to stories that the other
publications won't touch, on Vietnam, on
the CIA, on the FBI, on the Black
Panthers. And if we do it in a certain
way, the New York Times is going to have
to pick it up.
The expose about the NSA being used by
the CIA, that was a huge story. The NSA
was the National Student Association. It
was at that time the largest student
group. But the fact that the CIA was
directly involved in funding and
influencing the NSA was an eye openener
for a lot of people.
>> Mr. Hinkle, when did Ramparts first get
information regarding CIA activities and
student groups that started your
investigation?
uh approximately two months ago, we had
our first information on the story and
we've had a team of about uh 11
reporters and investigators working on
it full-time ever since.
>> I had been living in France. I was
married to a Frenchman and I I came home
and as I walked out of the airport,
there was a magazine stand and it had
Rampart's magazine there and on the
cover was a Native American woman named
Nana Means. She was against a
whitewashed wall where was written in
red letters better read than dead.
And I bought it and I read it and it
changed my life. It was an article by
Peter Collier who was then a progressive
person about the history of what white
European settlers had done to the
indigenous people that lived here that I
am ashamed to say I was not fully aware
of.
And it just rocked me and turned me into
an activist. I went to Alcatraz. It used
the occupation of Alcatraz, the Native
American occupation of the island of
Alcatraz to go back and tell the whole
history. And in that magazine was u
edited by Robert Shear.
>> Firing line with William F. Buckley Jr.
>> My name is C. [music] Dickerman Williams
and I shall act as chairman of this
discussion between Mr. Buckley and Mr.
Shear. The subject is is Ramparts
anti-American?
Mr. Shear, will you answer Mr. Buckley's
question?
>> Well, before I answer his question, let
me just state my only problem with
anti-Americanism is that I don't suspect
that your concept of what the core of
being an American and mine would be uh
the same. If we if you could come up
with such a very simple def and clear
definition of what an American is, then
I'm willing to talk about
anti-Americanism. I uh if you want for
purposes of rhetoric, I'm perfectly
willing to use the term. I find your
support of the government of South
Africa and Rhdesia and the Dominican
Republic and the DM regime to be
anti-American. But I'm I'm also willing
to concede that we can have a serious
disagreement about what Americanism is.
>> Correct. Correct. I I note uh and remark
your digression and return if you don't
mind to the subject under discussion.
>> Well, why is that a digression? I don't
see it as a digression.
>> Unless you're willing to define the term
anti-American, we're going to sit here
for an hour piddling around this
>> because I'm not talking about South
America. I'm talking about America. No,
but but but if you're not willing to
define what you mean by that term, then
it doesn't seem to you should use it.
Why wait until 20 minutes from now to
define it?
>> I'm quite willing to define it, but uh
but I I'm rather enjoying your
embarrassment.
>> I don't feel the least bit embarrassed.
I I I would rather talk about about your
substantive issues. I might add
>> I also find his contempt for freedom,
his support of the McCarthy Committee,
the House on American Activities
Committee, and his own red baiting and
his own attacks on anyone who desents in
the society. And in fact, his efforts to
make a person who was a communist to
become a non-person in much the same way
as the Soviet Union. Wait, wait, wait.
Don't go on and on and on and on.
>> What is the piece of writing that I'm
proudest of?
It's probably my letter from NonPen.
And I'm not saying it's the most
important, but I was there in Nonpen,
you know, for a conference of
Indo-Chinese people [music] and everyone
was there. the Vietkong were there and
North Vietnamese and Prince Cino, the
head of Cambodia, addressed this
conference and and so I was the only
American journalist [music] there. I
wrote a piece. It was a basically leave
it alone. I wrote this piece really more
to the left than anyone else. I said,
you know, let it be. Let let them make
their own history. Let them figure it
out, you know. And then I went back
there next year with Stanley Shine Bam
and my wife Anne.
>> But I think but for Bobby and I, we fell
in love with Cambodia. It was just
everything was lush, you know, so you
could so live off the land and it was
like, you know, a very underdeveloped
country, extraordinarily so, but there
was a peacefulness
and a um
a spirituality.
And then [music] to see what the US did,
the bombing of Cambodia was just
And in fact that's propelled the [music]
Camarouche to power and I know that I
mean I've studied it and it's just it's
again part of the empire and all the
horrors we've committed as an empire.
But [music] I think for Bobby and I and
for a lot of our generation I mean the
relationship we had with Vietnam and
Cambodia was extremely deep.
>> Dr. King was having lunch at the airport
with a friend and he was flipping
through some magazines
and he he happened to see a Ramparts
magazine and it was a photo essay called
the children of Vietnam and it showed
some of the effects of you know the US
war um on the Vietnamese especially the
toll that it took on Vietnamese
children. Ramparts was famous for having
run these photographs of napal children,
these terrible [music]
wounds that they they had and their
faces burned off practically off.
And the the question was, do we run
these photographs cuz they were so
gruesome? Is that sensationalist to run
something like this? This is the kind of
thing you see it and then you don't
sleep that night, you know, was
horrific. And to think that our
government was doing this, you know,
>> it was very hard-hitting
and he sort of pushed his food away and
he said, "I don't think I'm going to be
hungry until, you know, we do something
about this situation." Now, his his
advisers told him, "Don't come out
against our policy in Vietnam."
And Dr. King said, "No." And he later
said, "As soon as I saw that issue of
Ramparts magazine, I knew that I had to
come out and oppose our policy in in
Vietnam."
And you know, that was a kind of turning
point for him. [music] And you don't get
a lot of stories like that, but ramparts
h could have that kind of impact. There
were people in the civil rights
movement, "Get in your lane, Martin. You
got to stay in your lane." you know, and
then the White saying, "You got to stay
in your lane." Well, the New York Times
editorially, stay in your lane. And they
didn't even give him the courtesy of a
serious news account of his speech. And
when I listened to the speech and I read
it, you know, I said, "Wow, this
incredible manifesto. What I mean, this
is lays it out there." And it was like a
big deal to get a text of it so we could
publish it in Rampart. Well, that's one
of the reasons why the the FBI and the
CI and everybody came after us. When you
look at all the documents around that
have been revealed, they went after
because he had two adviserss, one black
guy and one Jewish guy who was supposed
to have once been communist. Red baiting
was the norm. What they did to Martin
Luther King, that was the deep state.
That was the FBI, which liberals are now
celebrating. But it was the FBI that
tried to kill King. They're the ones who
made the phony documents. They're the
ones who wanted to get him to commit
suicide.
We were followed all the time by both
the CIA and the FBI. And by the way, as
a personal note, uh I was exonerated by
Jed Gahoover. Uh there's something
called a sheer file in 1972 in the big
fight developed between the CIA and the
FBI about whether I was an agent of some
foreign government. And and they
couldn't find any government because as
soon as they settled on one, I would
denounce it. And uh and so the the FBI
agents in San Francisco said, "Dude,
she's just a good time Charlie. He he
just wants to find girls or something,
you know." Uh and we we he's denounced
in every single group that we've
infiltrated, you know, and and so
finally and so Jay Ed Guma came back
from Washington. They said, "We'll plant
some drugs on him." And the guys in San
Francisco had the wisdom to say, "Are
you kidding? will make him a national
hero. [laughter]
And so I there is actually
correspondence I finally got from the
Freedom of Information where Jahoo tells
the FBI agents in San Francisco that
he's closing the share case, closing my
file because he's not an enemy agent and
the CIA accused Hoover of betraying the
security of the country.
The thing he's most proud of with
Ramparts, I think he would tell you, is
um getting Martin Luther King to come
out against the war in Vietnam. But what
was interesting about that from a news
media point of view is that the news
media did not
grasp the importance of these two
national movements joining together, the
civil rights movement and the
antivietnam war movement joining
together like that. We burned our our
draft cards. We took our own draft
cards, burned them, and that was the
cover. Four top editors. So, we were
hauled before a federal grand jury in
New York because of that.
In San Francisco, I was hauled before
another grand jury over the Panthers.
Most people view the mass arrest as
being peaceful and that people went into
the uh buses in a peaceful way, but in
fact, as far as the treatment of the
prisoners in Santa was most brutal
that's taken place in the northern
United States, as far as I know. Yeah, I
was arrested accidentally even though I
had a press pass and then found myself
in the bus. And when we got to Sanorita,
we piled out of the bus and they began
hitting us. And then they instructed
everyone who had been arrested yesterday
to lie down and uh on some gravel
outside in this courtyard. It was very
cold and if we moved, if you moved your
feet or anything, they would hit you and
they would ask us questions. If we gave
the wrong answers, we'd be hit or we'd
have to crawl around our knees.
>> Crawl literally.
>> Yes. One of the medical volunteers was
in our barrack this morning and he
wouldn't give the right answer to a
question about who started this whole
frackus and they just pulled him right
out and started beating him very badly
and he was bleeding
and so Rampart sends Bobby to the Middle
East to go he went to Israel, Palestine,
Egypt and um he ended up writing a
series of articles which were extremely
fair and balanced. One thing that was
very clear to me was the Palestinians
were the victims from all sides. So yes,
I wrote very much out of a feeling of
concern for the Palestinians.
It's how I was raised as a Jew
[laughter]
was have some universal sense of values.
You know, I think if you go back and
look at those articles, I think they
hold up pretty well. Um but a lot of
people were upset by them including some
of the some of the pe some of the
investors
>> Marty Paris he basically pulled all the
money out of Ramparts and then other
people I think maybe they felt it tilted
to be too pro Arab. So anyway, a lot of
money went down the drain,
>> but Ramparts was able to reorganize
and relaunch without Warren and Bob was
in charge. But in short order, uh, Peter
Collier and David Horowitz led a kind of
insurrection
and they actually deposed Bob.
>> Well, it's interesting about David
Horowitz. First of all, I met David when
I was in graduate school Berkeley and we
got friendly and we were both on the
left. I brought him back from London to
be at Ramparts and uh [laughter]
David being the wy troski knightist
uh began plotting my overthrow uh as the
editor. The critical opportunity for him
is when I went off to see Eldridge in
Algeria.
Harowitz had the wonderful opportunity
to organize the staff and to uh argue
that I was being excessively paid and
leading a bourgeoa life and it was all
was funny because later in life he would
attack me from the right then he was
attacking me from the left.
>> I think he was a little bitter about it.
I think he felt betrayed because he had
recruited these people but he had to
reinvent himself. he had to try to
figure out how can I still be radical in
my thinking and yet keep the mainstream
audience and Ramparts was the exception
to the rule and that Ramparts had um
reached a pretty huge audience without
giving up its soul you know and then but
that's not the norm so I think he
started thinking well the way I can get
a magazine or a publisher interested is
to have these profiles these
interactions then that's where he
develops that skill
when I was in my final year uh as a
senior at Cal um he was recovering from
having been uh overthrown in a kind of
coup at Ramparts magazine a number of
years earlier. Uh he was trying to fight
his way out of being blacklisted by so
many uh publications and he was
beginning to [music] get some jobs again
writing for Esquire and for Playboy.
He had a book contract with McGra Hill
and he needed someone to help him with
that and I was enormously flattered.
Came over to the house and uh since then
we've been sort of in each other's lives
for the next 41 years.
>> Later, right, this is now when I'm
nine years old, 1976. Bob does the
interview with Jimmy Carter where Jimmy
Carter says uh he has lust in his heart
which even as a nine-year-old I thought
what's the big deal you know but
>> but this is a biblical image we all have
lust in our heart lust is what the
goddamn Bible you know the Old Testament
is certainly all about is lust
and uh so he was giving a thoughtful
answer you know instead that became the
hot item. This interview blows up
immediately and Bob is on TV a lot and I
can remember my mom waking me up at like
6:45 in the morning before school and
saying, "Your dad's on Good Morning
America." And I would drag my blanket
out to the couch and watch my dad have
one of those faceoff kind of [music]
interviews.
>> Robert Shear says no. He's an editor of
New Times magazine. He wrote the Playboy
interview uh with Jimmy Carter. Good
morning to you both. Bob becomes famous
because of the Jimmy Carter interview,
but of course he was already famous. But
to me, even as a nine-year-old, I was
like, "This is different." Like, you
just interviewed this guy running for
president and you may have changed the
whole election.
I mean the biggest thing that like my
father was struggling with at least from
my view or one of the things he was
struggling in the 70s was everybody who
came out of the 60s as a radical or a
leader was fighting with the deal with
the word sellout right everybody was a
sellout so you know I heard about you
know Tom Hayden becoming a sellout when
he went into mainstream politics and um
that was the word everybody would use
being a sellout sell so of course if you
go and take money
>> but I think the basic element in the
American constitutional experiment
was the right and obligation to question
authority in every realm
beginning with government and uh and
that's why the free press right is
enshrined there along and the big shift
I've seen is we had a flowering probably
the greatest
most significant pervasive time of the
flowering of that ideal in the 60s
and where it spread very far into very
different sectors.
Apart from the civil rights movement,
part from the women's movement, part
from the anti-war movement, lots of
different things culturally, emergence
of a new music, all sorts of things
without glorifying it, without glossing
over its contradictions. There's never
been a better period to talk about the
flowering of that kind [music] of
freedom, individual responsibility,
question authority. And the signal, the
slogan [snorts] of that was, don't sell
out. Don't sell out.
At one point we had a drink in the hotel
Al Gangquin, famous for hosting the
Algangquin round table made famous by
the contributors to The New Yorker. And
we sat there uh drinking steadily into
the uh we hours. And as the place uh
emptied of people, suddenly our eyes
fell upon a New York rat making its way
across the carpet. And shear looked at
the rat, looked up at me, and said, "You
know, Waserin, the rats are in the
toniest places, and they're here to
remind us all that the corruptions of
the place cannot be banished by the
conceits of how well-appointed they
are." And it is that sensibility that
has enabled Bob to be armored against
selling out, a word or phrase you barely
hear anymore.
When I first came to LA to work for the
LA Times and I thought, you know, am I
selling out now? What am I doing? Mass
media. I've done ramp parts and so
forth. You're one of the one of the
first people I interviewed here. And you
told me something then. You said,
"They're always going to pressure you.
Your ethics are always going to be on
the line." He said, "And what keeps me
straight?" I got You had this
oldfashioned typewriter. He said, "You
see this piece of paper? No one can stop
me from putting that piece of paper in
there, rolling it, and typing something
else. You said you're basically a
writer. Have we lost whatever moral
fiber we had or
>> Well, you haven't. What if I suggested
to you uh when you were talking about
looking for a hero that you look a
little more often in a mirror
>> because I think I am not interesting.
I'm sorry. Okay. I am a journalist
because what I write about is
interesting. This world is interesting.
I try to do it with feeling. I can't
control my feeling. I get pissed off. I
get angry. I want to write about it.
Okay. But I am the journalist.
>> I was asked by my metro editor if I knew
Bob Sheer. So my editor said, "Can you
go out to lunch with Bob and kind of
talk up the place because we're trying
to hire him." him and I said, "Wow,
that's surprised me because Bob was an
alternative journalist and at the paper
the LA Times was pretty stayed, you
know." But by then Bob was pretty well
known as a national correspondent
because of the Jimmy Carter interview
mostly. The LA Times decided to hire Bob
to do narrative journalism for the
paper.
>> I was brought along uh about a year
after as his researcher. I tried to make
sure that the facts were right. Shear
was always someone who had tremendous
regard, tremendous respect. Facts
mattered.
Uh he he labored under the tyranny of
facts because of course he lived in fear
that if he got something wrong, he would
be subjected to the most vicious kind of
red baiting.
>> I started off editing all of Bob's stuff
and I remember the first story I edited.
We were at we were in our apartment and
I started reading it and there were so
many spelling errors.
Bob had all these stories about when he
was a child about
flunking out of classes and this and
that and then he took a test in New
York. He went to school in the Bronx. He
took a test where he ended up getting
like one of the highest grades in
[music] the whole city of New York. He
went from being in the dummy class to
being in the genius class in one
afternoon.
>> So I go from the [__] class to the
genius class with this whole not a word
of explanation of what's going on. And
by now I have real behavioral problems
because I've gone through these two
years at PS89 and now I'm in high school
and I'm yeah I got anger issues and I
you know a lot of things and uh but
anyway so I go to this genius class and
she says oh and the co-curriculum class
here you do follow your own interest.
This was like John Dewey to the extreme,
you know, going to totally go with your
interest and here you can do whatever
you want. And I said, "Whatever I want."
She said, "Yeah, a little belligerent."
And she I said, "I want to go home." She
said, "Oh, you can." So she made the
mistake [laughter]
of giving me some p pass to go home. I
didn't come back for I don't know 6
weeks or something, two months. And the
truent officer came looking and got me.
And it was hard for him to but he never
put it together. [music] He never
realized that he had a learning
difference until our son was diagnosed.
>> So I had this yes undiagnosed
problem.
And the system did its best to try to
convince me I was dumb, but it made me
argumentative.
And it's actually been the main strength
I've had as a pmicist or critic. So Bob
um came out [music] as being dyslexic
publicly in a column he wrote for the
Times
and I I cannot to this day read that
without crying [music] because it was so
human and so uh painful what he was
describing his childhood and our son
Josh
>> think yeah go ahead because we don't
we're going to run out of time. One
reason I'm teaching I don't know that's
probably the main reason actually I got
involved in teaching was to help kids
with learning disability and it's
probably my greatest success is reaching
out to kids who learn a different way or
have a gap. Bob truly loves his
students, loves his class, and brings
subjects to life. And he's prepared to
argue every side of an issue so that
when he has a guest there, the guest may
take a position that one would expect
Bob to agree with, but then Bob is as
orary as he can possibly be trying to
make sure that the students are exposed
to the other side of that issue. He he
made us think, you know, he didn't just
present ideas and say one, he one, he
didn't present them and say that
anything is the right way to do or the
wrong way to do. He just made us think
about how we should be processing the
information we're being fed. And so
that's what's key about Bob's class. Bob
is sort of the quest for the truth.
Whatever that what I think is whatever
that truth may be, you know, so he's not
he doesn't think he's always right. And
that's why he'll play devil's advocate
on all the sides to sort of bring about
the lively debate. I a masters in public
diplomacy specifically because of Bob
Sheer.
The LA Times had attacked me when I ran
for Congress viciously and not just
editorially in their news section. Uh
paper had been quite conservative
and it was Nixon's paper, you know, and
yet clearly it was becoming a much
better paper. Otis Chandler was the best
publisher the paper ever had. He picked
a couple of very good editors to work
with, Nick Williams and then Bill
Thomas, who for my money was the best
editor around.
And uh they said, "We want you to do
what you do."
There were only a couple of times
at the LA Times where I had these
moments of truth during the 17 years
that I was a national reporter. And most
I mean, every time it worked out the way
we had promised. Uh, one time I
interviewed George Bush. It was in the
80 campaign and it derailed his campaign
uh because he talked about winnable
nuclear war and so forth. Well, he was
livid and so he came into the building
however after that I came into the
building. you have him speak to the
editorial board and political writers
and and so forth. I was invited and you
know said hello to him uh you know and
you know I had traveled with him when he
was not the most prominent candidate. So
he gave the speech and and to the board
and they one question was uh you know do
you uh think age will be an issue
Ronald Reagan's age
and he said uh well I'm not going to
bring it up and you know the 11th
commandment Republican candidates and
then out of nowhere he says
but
you know being older do you think at
Ronald Reagan's age will he be able to
withstand the pounding you get from a
reporter like Robert Shear who blah
blah, you know, everybody in the room is
startled, you know, and oh, you know,
Jesus. And then another question came up
a few questions later like that where he
in a gratuitous way dragged me into it.
And so as we were filing out of this
room, Otis Chandler, you know, came up
to me, put his arm around me. He was
taller than I am. Put his arm. He says
he said Bob said uh I've known George
since college. You got the right George.
Don't let this get to you. Just keep
doing it.
>> But Bob interviewed him. He interviewed
of course Reagan. Now
>> you believe we could survive a nuclear
war.
>> No. Because we have let them get so
strong and we have let them violate the
agreement.
>> But let's say we got stronger than them
again. Do you think we could survive a
nuclear war with the right underground
shelter systems, with the right defense
systems? Could we survive them? It would
be a survival of some of your people and
some of your facilities that you could
start again. It would not be anything
that I think in our society we would
consider acceptable. But then we have a
different regard for human life than
those monsters do.
>> He interviewed Nixon, too. Nixon liked
something Bob had written and invited
Bob to interview him.
>> The biggest challenge of all was Richard
Nixon. biggest challenge from an
interview point of view and and you know
Nixon's case you know my taxes had been
audited by this guy you know my life had
been you know people had been following
me all over the world because of this
guy you know and everything I mean I was
really on the receiving end of a a lot
of bad stuff for Nixon and I certainly
knew other people whose lives had been
destroyed and you know I knew a lot
about Cambodia he'd ordered the
Cambodian bombing I've been in Cambodia
beginning in 196 63 64 you know I loved
Cambodia I know the damage that the
terrible you know genocide and
everything
>> he would pick subjects that he just
thought were interesting and weren't
being covered right weren't being
covered at all and then he would bring
light to them.
The good humor truck circles aimlessly
through silent blocks of burned out
buildings, [music]
hunting the occasional waif still
playing in the rubble, who might yet
desire [music] a popsicle.
This time there is no sign of life and
[music] the ice cream truck departs with
a last ring of its merry chimes, leaving
a still life of the South Bronx [music]
warscape dotted by garbage lakes, dunes
of litter and beached hulks of abandoned
[music] cars. The streets are dead as if
locust had descended and slurped up the
ring alivio and stick ball [music]
games. The philosophers of the benches,
the checker kings and the loud music
boys, the girls with fishnet stockings
and stiletto heels, and the young studs
with bodies [music] some said were good
for nothing but dancing.
Gone the wild, chaotic, noisy,
cosmopolitan [music]
life of a burrow that for decades
belched up life continuously as its very
mission.
Bob became very interested in AIDS,
covering AIDS because nobody was
covering AIDS. Reagan, in fact, did very
little to recognize AIDS as a as a
crisis. I remember I I came home one
night from work, his mother lived with
us, and I said, um, Ida, I said, "You
look sad. What's wrong?" And she said,
"Oh, I'm so depressed. I'm reading this
book. It's so depressing." And I said,
"What are you reading?" And she said,
"This book about a disease called AIDS."
And I said, "Ida." I said, "You don't."
I said, "You're 82 or something." I
said, "You don't have to read about a
book like that about AIDS." And she
said, "Everybody should read this book."
And she was, that's where Bob gets a lot
of his [laughter]
who he is is from this woman. Anyway,
um, but Bob wrote about AIDS before
anybody in the country was writing about
AIDS. He did a whole series on AIDS.
He did a series on one of his early
stories, the television news industry.
when TV news was getting kind of really
toward entertainment more than news.
>> It was a wonderful series that he did.
At that time I was a lawyer specializing
in communications law and uh and Bob
series Bob's series won the Pulitzer
from the jury unanimously but the uh
overall Pulitzer committee did not allow
him to get the award that year. So the
board overturned it and gave it to
another reporter from the LA Times for a
series on dam safety.
>> It might have been related to the fact
that he had given an interview uh in
Moore magazine which was then kind of a
Columbia Journalism Review type magazine
in which he advocated guerilla
journalism and some people thought that
somehow that was suggesting a type of
journalism that they couldn't embrace.
>> Bob was nominated for 11 Pulitzers in 10
years.
You like potato.
>> And you like potato.
>> You like tomato
>> and you like tomato.
>> Potato.
>> Potato. [singing]
>> Tomato.
>> I feel that what made the show work is
that these were our views. We didn't
really have to prepare for it. Both Bob
and I had a syndicated column. H. Matt
Miller um wrote a lot himself. So, it's
always much easier to be on radio and
express your views when you're also a
writer because when you write, you
figure out
um your views in a in a deeper way.
>> She was on the right in the beginning.
He was on the left and uh then she
started moving over. So, they had to
kind of say she was in the center and
they had to get another person on the
right. When I started, I was on the
right and then I moved um in a position
that I described as beyond left and
right. At the time, I was a kind of
extinct
species of Republican. You know, I was
pro-choice, progay rights, pro gun
control. So, where we differed was on my
understanding at the time of the role of
government. I thought the private sector
would step up to the plate and address
all the social problems we're dealing
with. And gradually
and to a large extent through my
conversations with Bob, I realized that
would never happen that we actually
needed uh the raw power of government
appropriations to be able to address all
the problems we're facing.
She has spoken in Bob's class and she
said, "It was your professor who
influenced me. He made it all sound so
sensible what he was saying and
writing."
>> So Bob was
both a great friend and um an amazing
mentor.
>> Shear is terrific on the stump, you
know, passionate. And you know, one of
the things about Bob that is really
important is that he has proceeded all
his life as if the stakes were really
high, as if serious things actually
matter.
>> You know, I I like David Harvest
personally. I liked him at the time. I
did not think that he wrote the best
book about Vietnam, but he certainly had
the best title of any book about
American politics, the best and the
brightest.
That is the beginning of wisdom about
the American condition.
The great damage in our society comes
from the best and the brightest.
I had two fears
during my years as Secretary of Defense.
One fear, and I expressed it to
President Johnson in December 1965, was
that we couldn't win the war militarily.
I said to him at that time and I quote
it in the book, there's only a one in
three chance or at best a one in two
chance to win militarily. He said, "Are
you saying we can't win military?" I
said, "Yes." However, the second fear
was that if we pulled out of Vietnam, it
would lead to what Eisenhower predicted
in 1954, the fall of the dominoes. In
other words, the fear that if we didn't
stand firm, the communists [music] would
take control of Southeast Asia, all of
Asia, and strengthen their position
against the [music] West in in Europe
and the US.
>> I think the book is a very important
one, and I think it's important because
it shows how little knowledge, the
abysmal ignorance that was present uh in
the government at that time that it
shows us that the best and the brightest
did not read and did not think very
clearly. makes one suspicious of any
government official uh and I think
should lead the citizens to question uh
what they're told is the official truth.
First of all, there were senators uh
Gruning and Moss and Church who were
saying all these things that McNamara
now says he didn't know that Ho Chi Min
was an Asian Tito that there was a SOS
Soviet dispute. We installed Yemen power
this autocrat who McNamera says he
detested as an autocrat and later we had
killed.
But I don't find any sense of contrition
in this book. I think it's a bit
cold-blooded in its rhetoric. Uh there's
no real sense of the lives that were
lost, the damage to this country. Uh the
people who the American military who
were killed or were kept prisoner, the
Vietnamese who died. What we have, I
think, is someone dissembling and trying
to put the best spin on is really an
atrocious complicity.
But there was in Bob a deliberate
renunciation
of the East Coast. a deliberate
renunciation of the cozy suffocations of
the Washington, New York, Boston nexus
and a deliberate embrace of a kind of
freewheeling west coast bohemianism. The
heady bohemianism of Furling Getty's San
Francisco
and of Berkeley in those days, I think
was a tonic to him.
I think it hurt him with respect to a
national reputation despite the fact
that he was a columnist for the Los
Angeles Times and despite the fact that
those columns would from time to time
get picked up. As I say, geography is
fate and the Los Angeles Times for all
its good reporting was still regarded by
most of the rest of the country as
provincial.
But the bottom line at the LA Times was
they're going to hire me because I add
something to their mix, which if they're
a commercial enterprise makes them
commercially more viable. Uh if they
need some kind of balance for whatever
reason, uh and then when they don't need
that, they fire you, you know, or when
there's too much of that, they fire you,
right? I mean, that's what it's all
about because their main concern is not
necessarily journalism or truth or
anything else. is some kind of mix that
they're marketing.
>> Last week, the Los Angeles Times
announced it's firing longtime columnist
Robert Shear. He's been at the Times for
30 years. He was one of the most
progressive voices there. In recent
years, his columns took on the Bush
administration and its justifications
for the invasion of Iraq. In a posting
at the Huffington Post blog, he wrote,
quote, "The publisher Jeff Johnson,
who's offered not a word of explanation
to me, has privately told people he
hated every word I wrote. I assume
mostly refers to my exposing the lies
used by President Bush to justify the
invasion."
Bob's whole thing with work has always
been you have to have more than one job
so you can tell people to [__] off if
they push you. You need to be
independent and able to walk away. And
the LA Times really tested that for him
because
he it was hard for him to just walk away
from that. He really valued having that
audience in this city. You know, he had
his political column once a week and he
had his local column which at one point
was two or I think twice a week and he
became a voice and a personality on the
west side of LA and got a lot out of
that. So that went away and then he lost
his column and I think he was pretty
devastated. He felt like that was his
home. He'd left his freelance career for
the most part to go to the LA Times. He
met his wife, my mom, at the LA Times.
I think it's a shabby business that the
LA Times let Bob go uh when, you know,
he came under some suspicion of writing
obsessively about our blunders in Iraq.
Take the recent post 911 experience. We
wouldn't have gone into Iraq, this place
we've made. Who ever thought we could
make Saddam Hussein look good?
You know, we're making Assad look good.
We're making Gaddafi look good. We can
make any monster in the world look good
by our efforts to bring democracy, you
know. We bring chaos. We bring madness.
It's absolutely insane, thoughtless, you
know, and and uh we have this this
ability. Why? Because we don't have an
informed public. You could lie to the
public about the basic two reasons for
going into Iraq. There were no weapons
of mass destruction. You knew it in real
time, but you lied. And secondly, uh you
lied about Saddam Hussein's connection
with al-Qaeda. It was the one place in
the Middle East where al-Qaeda could not
operate.
It's an absolute lie. And yet you make
this intervention.
The thing I think is so frustrating for
him is there's no prize for being right
after the fact. You know, on KCRW on
Left, Right, and Center, um, which was a
very popular show that lots of people
listen to. So, people will know for for
really years before and during the Iraq
war. Bob was
far outnumbered on the panel by people
who thought it was either a very good
idea to invade Iraq or it was going
swimmingly or it could very easily go
much better if only we would do X Y and
Z. And obviously Bob was 100% right
about the Iraq war. Um and so what?
There's no price for that. And in fact,
in addition to his career, Bob has had
to pay a price, I think, with his
friendships because a lot of people
that, you know, they go way back and
there's mutual love there, I think, had
a really hard time dealing with some of
his um issues. I think people don't
realize Bob is not a Democrat. He's not
a liberal. He's a person who has a um a
view of the world that's informed by his
experience growing up in poverty um in
in during the end of the depression and
World War II and through the 60s and the
and the civil rights movement. And that
is where his values come from. And he's
not loyal to a movement or a party. um
he he really has a basic test of human
decency and and that's more important to
him than um he doesn't see it as his job
to help someone become president.
Certainly uh and no journalist should
I come from a tradition on the left
where getting it right and I don't mean
in some doctrinire sense
was critical to your set of values.
IVF Stone would go to hearings and
report on him. He'd get the
congressional record. He'd get the
committee reports and documents and, you
know, read them with his glasses up by
his nose, you know, and uh that he did
that kind of work and then he'd throw it
back at them. And and that's where I
learned journalism uh from the
journalists that I really admired. Izzy
uh was not writing his columns because
it was going to make him a celebrity or
something. He was doing it because he
was trying to pursue the truth. Izzy
Stone did not accept at face value what
the administration said or the other
reporters, the Washington establishment
reporters said, but he would just dig
into everything and show that they were
wrong. Well, that's see that's what Bob
has. That's why Bob is a to me uh an
inspirational editor and he's able to
take a reporter like me and inspire me
to to do the same, you know, to dig dig
dig like the like the name of the site
says, truth dig,
>> truthdig.com. We really want to carry on
and do investigative journalism. we
landed on the idea of doing a website uh
and we came up uh together
collaboratively, you know, with the idea
of truth dig and it was in the works and
we had um kind of a prototype and we
were going to launch the beta version,
but in fact when he was fired from the
Los Angeles Times for his national
column and had so much public support,
it it propelled us to just like go ahead
and launch and take advantage of the
goodwill and continue his voice.
>> We call it truth dig because we think
that you can get to a truth that the
truth matters because lives are
sacrifice bad policies are followed and
so forth. You're also making the
assumption that ultimately a a public in
a democratic society will value the
truth, will find ways to support it.
Okay.
>> A lot of what he would do is just pick
up the phone and say, "Get this up on
the website. Um, this thing is
happening. People need to be talking
about it. Why aren't we writing more
about Gaza, for example, the many times
that Israel bombed Gaza or, you know,
shot at people from across the border
or, you know, that was just generally in
the news." He say, "This is a taboo
subject, but people aren't talking about
it. It's crazy what's happening. We
should be talking about it." and he
would call call us up and he would say,
"I've got this writer who's going to
write about this or go find a writer who
can write about this or I'm going to
write about this." And he would force it
up on the site even if we were, you
know, to say, "Oh, we already have a
schedule and we can't really fit that in
right now." He would he really is a
toughy at Truth Dig. He's the boss and
he really will insist that things go up
that people should be talking about.
[music]
>> Our first really great story was one I'm
very proud of. It concerned the death of
Pat Tilman uh or football professional
football player. He and [music] his
brother Kevin has joined the Rangers.
The idea of being ordinary people should
not have to bear the price of war. Even
athletes. [music]
Kevin was a baseball player, Cleveland
Indian system. And they went to
Afghanistan and uh Pat was killed in an
incident that was [music] first lied
about as if you know it was a heroic
thing. He was heroic but not uh that's
[music] not the way he died. He died
because of American troops and then
there's a lot of suspicion about that
which I have to this day. I had [music]
written a column about it. My wife ended
up writing a book.
Kevin Tman, Pat's brother, uh wrote a
piece about the meaning of Pat's death
and the reaction to it. When that came
out, you had Wolf Blitzer walking over
to his computer and saying, "This major
story just broke on this little website,
Truth Dig." And and actually on CNN
showed an image of uh the Truth Dig
website. And you had the AP doing
several stories on it. It was the
Washington Post biggest story. The New
York Times then did a story. And so it
just went viral
>> and it took us off the charts. that
established trustic. We've won six
Webbies, the internet award for we've
been the best political website,
[applause]
Wall Street, what [__] thieves.
You also have to uh divorce
his and his speeches, you know, that he
that he makes from uh the kind of
journalism that that he does like his
work on the banks, digging into the
financial the whole financial picture
and the runup to the recession and who
profited from that was really pioneering
stuff. I mean other people were doing he
wasn't the only one but other people
were doing it but that kind of
journalism and he was a leader in that
uh set the stage for a critical thinking
of the bailout and really was the
intellectual background of the Sanders
campaign.
The LA Times used to be called the
velvet coffin. We actually flew first
class. We actually stayed at good
hotels, you know, but the economy of
that couldn't even been sustained
without the internet. Already the profit
margins were declining. The internet
came in and just unmasked the whole
thing. Okay, online journalism is not
paying for anyone. That's why I wrote
this whole book about they know
everything about you. One of the things
in that book is that the disruption of
print did not create a self- sustaining
operation or model to take its place
because uh advertising on the internet
is tiny compared to the cost. Uh and
that is because the advertisers don't
have to go to you. They don't have to go
to New York Times. They can pick up your
readers by data mining. I think the most
disturbing thing is that our CIA could
go in and do data mining. uh government
leaks become more important. If if
information is more difficult to obtain
because it's costly by news
organizations and they can't send
reporters out to cover the war, the
government will always be more than
willing to give you information. So
there's that whole element, a rising
power of governments all over the world,
their ability to control news and uh a
lack of independent alternative
organizations.
>> I do a podcast now for KCW. I have to
help raise the money for it
>> to still the idea get behind public
radio and television.
We should be able to find the ability to
support a strong robust public media
that's not just television or radio, but
that's also the internet that people can
access, that they can learn on, that
they can participate in. Everybody talks
about the internet being so
irresponsible because anybody can put
something out. Well, that's what the
great pamphleteing tradition in America
was all about. If you could find
somebody to print on their letter press
your rights of man your document, you
could find a big audience. You know,
this is how our declaration of
independence got circulated. The press
that's enshrined in our constitution,
our first amendment, free press was
often a scurless press. It was made up
of town criers and dissident and
pamphleteers.
Fake news is a term that um is dangerous
because it pulls in a lot of different
desperate things. Like there's a in the
truest sense it's right. It's people who
are paying to have literal fake news on
literally fake news websites created and
then promoted on Facebook for various
means whether it's financial gain or
political uh gain. And then there are
sites like Truth Dig that have a very
deliberate point of view. I think the
it's important for people to value
journalism and resist genuine fake news,
but it also has been used as a way of
dismissing progressive media outlets and
conservative media outlets.
>> I would say the most overwhelming
feeling I had about journalism in
America and I have it about the
university as well. I have been in
totalitarian countries where people do
get their fingernails pulled out. They
do get their genitals crushed. They do
get put into terrible conditions. But
when I look at my colleagues, I always
think, you know, your fingernails are
not being torn out, you know, and your
family is not going to be targeted for
murder that we know of. I mean, it's not
but it's not really in your mind. We're
talking about some, you know, kink in
your career trajectory, you know. So
then I say, "Shame on you." And that
goes for all the people who didn't tell
us what Edward Snowden told us or
Chelsea Manning or Daniel Ellburg, why
weren't there more of this?
We have a clearly established principle
that if you think crimes have been
conducted in your name by your
government, you know, the killing of
innocents in Iraq, which was motivated
Bradley Manning, or intruding on
people's privacy and manipulating them,
that you have an obligation to speak up.
You have an obligation uh to express
that. And if you feel the channels are
blocked, and they certainly are in
connection with the National Security
Agency, there are no channels for an
individual to speak up, then you have an
obligation to become a whistleblower.
That's not some foreign notion. That's
something that came out of our
tradition.
That's our law. We held people
accountable. And I think we should
recognize what we have at stake here is
that there are some brave souls that
think freedom is non-negotiable.
It defines their soul, their essence,
their commitment, their moral core, and
they're going to be true to it, and we
should back them.
I had one commitment to myself to the
degree that I am a public person. I'm
giving a speech. I'm writing something.
I'm teaching.
I want to be as honest as I possibly can
be and not betray the trust that people
are putting in me. For me, that was the
highest obligation.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Lawrence Ferling getting my favorite
quote. Keep [music] an open mind, but
not hoping your brains fall out.